Guide to the Gil Green Papers TAM.095
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gil Green Papers
1925-1993
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Green, Gil, 1906-
Green, Ralph
TAM.095
14 Linear Feet in 11 record cartons and 7 manuscript boxes.
Gil Green (1906-1997) was a Communist, a Smith Act defendant, and a prominent figure in the Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA) through 1991. As a youth, he joined the Young Workers League (later the Young Communist League) eventually becoming its national secretary. From 1941-1945 and again from 1966-1968, Green was head of the Communist Party in New York State and also briefly headed the Party in Illinois. Convicted under the Smith Act in 1949, Green was imprisoned from 1956 until 1961. He left the Party in 1991 and helped to found the Committees of Correspondence. The Gil Green Papers date from 1949 to 1993 and include Green's correspondence, writings, and documentation of his political activities. The collection also contains a large amount of FBI files obtained by Green through Freedom of Information Act requests. These files relate primarily to the FBI's investigations of Green's work with the CPUSA and his prosecution under the Smith Act.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Gil Green, circa 1980 and 1993. The accession number associated with these gifts is 1980.010. In 1981, the Chicago Historical Society sent Tamiment Library two boxes of photocopies of Gil Green's prison correspondence. There is no accession number associated with this gift. Green sent an additional seven boxes of FBI files to the Tamiment Library in 1982. Additional FBI files were presumably sent to Tamiment sometime around 1993. There is no accession number associated with these materials. A letter from Gil Green to Robby Cohen was found in repository in April of 2014 and added to this collection. The accession number associated with this document is 2014.049.
Custodial History
Gil Green donated portions of his personal papers to both the Tamiment Library and the Chicago Historical Society, circa 1980. In 1981 the Chicago Historical Society created photocopies of Green's prison correspondence, which were sent to the Tamiment Library to be included in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Gil Green (1906-1997), born Gilbert Greenberg in Chicago, the son of working class Russian-Jewish immigrants, was a Communist youth leader in the 1930s, a member of the Communist Party's Politburo, a Smith Act defendant, and the chief figure of a reformist current in the CPUSA through 1991. Green joined the Young Workers League (later the Young Communist League) in 1924, and shortly thereafter, the Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA). He rose through the ranks, and in 1932 became national secretary of the YCL, a position he held throughout the decade. As secretary of the YCL he trained a generation of Party cadres and led the League to a position of influence in the 1.7 million-member American Youth Congress. In 1935 he attended the Comintern's Seventh Congress, where he was an advocate for the emerging Popular Front policy. In 1941 Green became head of the Party in New York State, but relinquished the title in 1945 due to his association with ousted Party head Earl Browder. Green later moved to Chicago where he headed the Illinois Party organization. Convicted under the Smith Act in 1949, Green became a fugitive, surrendered in 1956 and was released from jail in 1961. In 1966, Green once again became the head of the New York Party, but resigned in 1968 to protest the CPUSA's endorsement of the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia. He remained an elder statesman and locus of Communist Party reform currents until 1991, when he left the Party and helped to found the Committees of Correspondence, a social-democratic organization.
Works by Gil Green:
Marxism and the world today. New York: New York State Committee, Communist Party, n.d. 23 p.
Youth confronts the Blue Eagle. New York: Youth Publishers, November, 1933. 29 p.
United we stand: for peace and socialism. New York: Workers Library Publishers, 1935. 63 p.
Young Communists and the unity of youth. Speech delivered at the 7th World Congress of the Communist International. New York: Youth Publishers, October, 1935. 15 p.
Facing the 8th convention of the Young Communist League. Report, delivered Jan. 1, 1937. New York: Young Communist League, n.d.
Make your dreams come true. Report to the 8th national convention of the Young Communist League, New York City, May 2, 1937. New York: Workers Library Publishers, June, 1937. 47 p.
The truth about Soviet Russia. New York: New Age Publishers, March, 1938. 48 p.
America must act now! New York: Workers Library Publishers, November, 1941. 14 p.
New York State's wartime election. New York: New York State Communist Party, September, 1942. 24 p.
Marxism and the world today. New York: New York State Committee, Communist Party, [1944?]. 23 p.
The enemy forgotten. New York, International Publishers [1956]. 318 p.
Revolution Cuban style; impressions of a recent visit. New York, International Publishers [1970]. 125 p.
Terrorism - is it revolutionary? New York: New Outlook Publishers, 1970. 40 p.
The new radicalism: anarchist or Marxist? New York: International Publishers, 1971. 189 p.
What's happening to labor. New York: International Publishers, 1976. 305 p.
Portugal's revolution. New York: International Publishers, 1976. 99 p.
Cuba at 25: the continuing revolution. New York: International Publishers, 1983. 117 p.
Cold war fugitive: a personal story of the McCarthy years. New York: International Publishers, 1984. 275 p.
Scope and Content Note
The Gil Green Papers date from 1941 to 1993 and contain the correspondence, writings, and FBI files of Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA) leader and organizer Gil Green. His papers consist primarily of correspondence and FBI files released through Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests. Green corresponded with many like-minded communists, ex-communists, other U.S. leftists, historians, and researchers, and much of the correspondence in this collection relates to communist history and radical thought and activity. Several letters relate to Green's support of the Puerto Rican independence movement in the late 1970s and early 1980s. There is a small amount of personal correspondence between Green and his family, including photocopies of Green's correspondence during his five years in prison, 1956-1961. Green's prison correspondence largely consists of letters to his first wife (Lil Green, 1910-1964) and children, but also contains some letters with political associates and attorneys. The collection includes an assortment of unpublished typescripts, notes, and other materials related to Green's political career. Green's writing consist of speeches at Communist Party engagements, political essays and editorials, unpublished typescripts of books by Green and others, and several documents related to the publicity and reception of Green's books. A number of the FBI files in this collection were used by Green in preparation for his memoir, Cold War Fugitive, and were grouped by Green to facilitate his research. Green's FBI files make up the bulk of his collection and document government surveillance of his political activities from the late 1930s through the 1970s. The majority of these files focus on Green's affiliation with the CPUSA, the FBI's hunt for Green between 1949 and 1956, and his prison sentence. FBI files are accompanied by correspondence between Green, his attorney Edward Greer, and federal agencies regarding FOIA requests.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into four series: Series I. Correspondence, General; Series II. Correspondence, Prison; Series III. Political Activities, Associates, and Writings; Series IV. FBI and Prison Files. Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic or creator, with the exception of correspondence in Series II, which is arranged chronologically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
A portion of Gil Green's papers are also held at the Chicago History Museum Research Center in Chicago, Illinois. This collection is titled: Gil Green papers [manuscript], ca. 1947-1986. Call number: MSS Lot Green.
The Counterattack Research Files (TAM 148)
Series 50, file 33 (0.5 lf), is a compilation of documentation on the Illinois Communist Party, 1946-1950, and on Green's leadership thereof, including reportage and analysis by informants and government agents.
Sender Garlin Letters to Gil Green (TAM 536)
Existence and Location of Originals
Original copies of correspondence in Series II: Correspondence, Prison are held at the Chicago History Museum in the Gil Green Papers, MSS Lot Green.
Revolutionaries |z Puerto Rico.; Radicals |z Puerto Rico.; New York (N.Y.); Memoirs; Typescripts.; Czechoslovakia |x History |y Intervention, 1968.; Correspondence.; Communists -- United States.; Case files.; Lebrón, Lolita, 1919-2010; North, Helen Oken; Green, Lil, 1919-1954; Green, Gil, 1906-; Engelstein, David; Garlin, Sender; Healey, Dorothy, 1914-2006; Brown, Lloyd L. (Lloyd Louis), 1913-2003; Bridges, Harry, 1901-; Lens, Sidney; Hyndman, Kate; Young Workers League of America; United States. |t Alien Registration Act, 1940; Young Communist League of the U.S.; Schneiderman, William; Toohey, Pat; Communist Party of the United States of America; Wofsy, Leon; Wellman, Saul; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Green, Gil, 1906-; Green, Ralph
- Series I: Correspondence, General, 1949-1990; 1 Linear Feet
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains correspondence (most incoming, arranged alphabetically) with like-minded communists, ex-communists, other U.S. leftists, historians and other researchers, and is primarily concerned with communist history and with current events, radical thought and activity. There is also some family correspondence. Additionally, several letters relate to Green's support of organized labor and independence movements in Puerto Rico in the late 1970s and early 1980s. Prominent and/or principal correspondents include: Harry Bridges, Lloyd Brown, David Engelstein, Sender Garlin, Dorothy Healey, Kate Hyndman, Lolita Lebron and other Puerto Rican radicals, Sidney Lens, Helen North (his second wife), Paul Robeson Jr., Bill Schneiderman, Pat Toohey, Saul Wellman and Leon Wofsy. Folders labeled "Addendum" were moved into this series in 2016, following the consolidation of materials into Series I and Series II.
  - Amter, Nell, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aptheker, Bettina, 1971, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bender, Stanley, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boyte, Harry (New American Movement), 1974-1976, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bridges, Harry & Nikki, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brown, Lloyd, 1949-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Buhle, Paul, 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cohen, Milt, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Engelstein, David & Mary, 1972-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family and Family History, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Garlin, Sender, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Gates], Johnny: Gil Green "critical response to your open letter", 1969 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gerson, Si, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gordon, Max, 1983, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Green, Gil: Housing - Racial Discrimination, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Green, Gil: Letters to Editors, 1949, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Healey, Dorothy, circa 1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Historians, 1976-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hyndman, Kate, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kalter, Rose - re Dave Doran, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lebron, Lolita, 1981 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lens, Sidney, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Liveright, Betty and Herman, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Marquit, Erwin (GG to), 1988 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mello, Servio (Brazil), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1969-1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Navasky, Victor, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - North, Helen, 1966-1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pajetta, Giuliano (PCI member of Parliament), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Peck, Sid, 1960, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Puerto Rico - correspondence & FOIA documents, 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Richmond, Al, 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5A)
  - Robeson, Paul Jr. - GG ltr to, 1982 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 5B)
  - Rubin, Danny and Maurice [Spector], 1985, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sandy, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Schendel, Herman, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Schneiderman, Bill, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sennett, William, 1978-1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Toohey, Pat, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Wellman, Saul, 1977-1978, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Whitman, Alden, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wofsy, Leon, 1985-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Addendum - Englestein, David, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Addendum - Englestein, David Political-Ideological Letters to Gil Green, 1981-1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Addendum - Garlin, Sender, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, Prison, 1949-1961; 1 Linear Feet
  This series consists of copies of (mostly outgoing) letters between Gil Green and members of his family during his time in prison. The majority of the letters are addressed to Green's first wife, Lillian Green, and their children. There are also several letters between Gil Green and his brother Ben. These letters predominantly relate to personal issues, but also touch briefly on political topics in relation to Green's trial and sentence.
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1956 February-April (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence, 1956 May-December (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series III: Projects, Activities, Associates, Topics, 1949-1990; 1 Linear Feet
  This series contains unpublished typescripts by Green and others, notably James Allen's memoir Marxist Publishing (n.d., 44 pp.), A Labor Revolutionary in Detroit (re Nat Ganley), and Green's 1968 notes on his remarks on Czechoslovakia at the CP's Central Committee meeting thereon; editorial files pertaining to the writing, publication and reception of several of Green's later books, notably his autobiographical Cold War Fugitive (1984); third party correspondence of several of Green's political friends and associates, notably Lloyd Brown; and a file of Smith Act-related material obtained through Freedom of Information Act requests.
  - Allen, James - Marxist Publishing(memoir, 44 p. ts), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Lloyd - Correspondence with others, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Lloyd - Letters to the Editor (New York Times), 1959-1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chancey, Martin - The American Left in Disarray(ts, 20 p.), circa late 1970s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chile - Overthrow of Allende, undated (Box 5, Folder 4A)
  - Foster, notes on - by Arthur Zipser, undated (Box 5, Folder 4B)
  - Ganley, Ann - Reminiscences, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ganley, Nat: A Labor Revolutionary in Detroit - a Biographical Monograph by Michael Devereaux Whitty. 22 p., undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Ganley, Nat: Writings - published and unpublished, 1953-1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Green, Gil: An Aesopian Letter, circa 1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Green, Gil: Aristocracy of Labor, for Commission on, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Green, Gil: Contradictions in Developing Socialism (Berkeley - Marxist Scholars Conference), 1987 November 14 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Green, Gil: Cold War Fugitive- correspondence, reviews, etc., circa 1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Green, Gil: Contradictions in Developing Socialism. Berkeley, CA, Marxist Scholars Conference, 1987 November 14 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Green, Gil: Cuba at Twenty-Five: the Continuing Revolution correspondence, publicity, reviews, etc., 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Green, Gil: "Curriculum" (for a proposed Marxist school), circa 1977 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Green, Gil: Czechoslovakia - "Notes on my remarks in Central Committee discussion...", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Green, Gil: Democracy, the Key to Party Growth, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Green, Gil: If Justice Murphy Took the Stand, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Green, Gil: Reflections on Gus Hall's article, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Green, Gil: Report - New York State CP Committee Meeting, 1965 January 28-29 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Green, Gil: Smith Act-related FOIA documents & correspondence, 1948-1984 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Green, Gil: Summary of Four Lectures on Glasnost. Berkshire Forum, 1987 July 24-26 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Green, Gil: "U.S.A." - lesson plans, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Green, Gil: Thompson, Robert - Remarks at His Re-Burial at Arlington National Cemetery, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Green, Gil: "U.S.A." - Lesson Plans, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Green, Gil: What's Happening to Labor- correspondence, reviews, etc., circa 1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Green, Gil: Writings, Miscellaneous & Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Green, Lil: In Memoriam, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Hall, Gus (re): Reply to the Gus Hall Slander (Japanese CP), 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Harrington, Michael - research file, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Jacques, Jeffrey: "What is Socialism?", 1992 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Myerson, Michael - U.S. Peace Council 10th Anniversary, 1989 November 10 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Two Songs for the Exiles (to Gil Green and Henry Winston), undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Series IV: FBI and Prison Files, 1939-1993; 11.5 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  This series has been subdivided into three subseries based on the way in which these documents were maintained by Gil Green. Subseries IVA: FOIA Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by federal agency. Subseries IVB: Files Grouped By Green, have been maintained in the order established by Green. Subseries IVC: Files By Topic, are grouped roughly by topic of investigation or FBI office of origin.
  This series makes up the bulk of the collection and contains all of the files sent to Gil Green from federal agencies between 1978 and 1991 in response to his numerous Freedom of Information Act requests. They consist of FBI reports, correspondence between bureau offices, transcripts of trial proceedings and testimony, surveillance logs, and copies of documents produced by individuals and organizations under FBI surveillance. A large portion of these files deal with the FBI's hunt for Green between 1951 and 1956. During these years, Green was a political fugitive seeking to escape federal charges for violating the Smith Act. The series also contains a number of FBI files obtained through the efforts of Gil Green's attorney, Edward Greer, and contain FBI files from various regional offices and files on individuals affiliated with Green or the CPUSA between the 1930s and 1970s. FBI files contained in Subseries IVB were grouped by Green in preparation for his 1984 memoir, Cold War Fugitive: A Personal Story of the McCarthy Years. These files are heavily annotated and reflect the various stages of the FBI's campaign against Green. They do not, however, correspond with chapters in his book.
  Along with FBI files, Green received several hundred pages of documents from the Bureau of Prisons and Parole Board. These files contain copies of Green's personal notes and correspondence during his time in prison, as well as conduct reports, telephone logs, and parole board paperwork.
  Also included among these materials is a small amount of correspondence between Green, his attorney Ed Greer, and various federal agencies regarding Green's FOIA requests between 1975 and 1981, held in Subseries IVA.
  - Subseries IVA: FOIA Correspondence, 1949-1981; 0.25 Linear Feet
    - Bureau of Prisons, 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - CIA, 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Department of Justice, 1949-1956, 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Department of State, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Ed Greer, 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - FBI, 1976-1979 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - US Parole Commission, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Subseries IVB: Files Grouped by Gil Green, 1941-1971; 0.75 Linear Feet
    - The Family (Book I and II), 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
    - The Family (Book III) and Guatemala Story, National Underground, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
    - The Hunt: Mistaken Identities, Resumes, and FBI Directives (Book I), 1951 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
    - The Hunt: Mistaken Identities, Resumes, and FBI Directives (Book II), 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 14-15)
    - The Hunt: Mistaken Identities, Resumes, and FBI Directives (Book III & Book IV), 1952-1956 (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
    - The Hunt: Mistaken Identities, Resumes, and FBI Directives (Book IV), 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 18-19)
    - Surrender & After: Where Was I, Legal & Amnesty, and Rare Book Reviews, 1956-1962, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Personal Political Misc, 1941-1947 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries IVC: Files by Topic, 1925-1980; 10.5 Linear Feet
    This subseries contains sets of documents sent to Gil Green from the FBI as a result of his FOIA requests. These files range in size from ten to several hundred pages, and have been retained largely as they were received from the FBI. In some instances, certain pages have been excluded by the FBI. Where these exclusions occurred, the FBI included "FOIPA Deleted Information Sheets." Many sheets, however, were removed by Green to reduce bulk, and it may no longer be apparent where certain content has been omitted.
    Files in this subseries were sent to Green from both national and regional FBI offices. They document a wide array of topics related to Green's political activities between the 1930s and 1970s, including: Smith Act trials against members of the Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA), the FBI's search for Green and other Smith Act fugitives, Green's surrender to the FBI, Green's five-year sentence at Leavenworth prison, and surveillance of Green after his release. The files contain a variety of documents including: FBI field reports, correspondence between bureau offices, Smith Act trial transcripts, surveillance logs, and copies of documents produced by individuals or organizations under FBI surveillance. Files from regional offices largely relate to CPUSA activities in New York and Chicago. A large portion of these regional files consist of memoranda from the Special Agents in Command (SAC), who managed the FBI regional offices, and contain records of the FBI's surveillance of Green. Other files focus on individuals or organizations associated with Green, but may not relate to him directly. These files touch on a wide array of topics. Titles for these files address the general subject to which they relate, but because some vary so widely, references to certain topics or individuals may be scattered throughout.
    - Bureau of Prisons and Parole Board, 1948-1980 (Box 8, Folder 3-11)
    - Bureau of Prisons and Parole Board, 1958-1961 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Chicago FBI Office Files - Ben Green, 1944-1960 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Chicago FBI Office Files - Communist Activity, 1946-1959 (Box 9, Folder 3-7)
    - Chicago FBI Office Files - Communist Infiltration, 1940-1966 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Chicago FBI Office Files - Counterintelligence Program, CPUSA, 1943-1962 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Chicago FBI Office Files - CPUSA, 1946-1956 (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
    - Chicago FBI Office Files - Gil Green, 1949-1965 (Box 9, Folder 12-14)
    - Chicago FBI Office Files - Gil Green and Communist Fugitives, 1949-1951 (Box 9, Folder 15)